all right
[Music]
vitamin K wait I know about vitamins A B
C D and E
what happened to vitamins f g h i and J
it's not alphabetical vitamin K stands
for coagulation or at least it does in
German
that's the fundamental role vitamin K
plays helping the blood to clot but over
the last few decades there's evidence
that it has other roles in the health of
our bones heart and brain
kind of reminds me of vitamin D I mean
we know vitamin D is important for bone
health but then there's been all sorts
of other controversial functions
ascribed to it some of which have been
proven and some disproven what about
vitamin K for bone health for example is
the link between vitamin K and
osteoporosis myth or reality
it turns out the findings on vitamin K
and Bone are conflicting and unclear it
doesn't help that some of the major
trials are found to be problematic to
say the least as in
likely fraudulent containing
impossible data with investigators
admitting to complete fabrication and so
if you do a systematic review
eliminating any fraud we find there's no
evidence of vitamin K supplementation
affects bone mineral density or
vertebral fractures
what about the heart vitamin K
supplementation for the prevention of
cardiovascular disease there's a vitamin
K activated protein in your blood that
binds up excess calcium and helps
prevent calcium from being deposited
into the walls of your arteries and
stiffening them so if you give people
extra vitamin K well that protect
people's arteries from calcification it
sounds good in theory but no vitamin k
does not appear to consistently prevent
progression of calcification
atherosclerosis or arterial stiffness
for example artery calcifications
particularly common in patients with
chronic kidney disease which can lead to
increased artery stiffness which is an
important risk factor for heart attacks
and strokes in earlier trial didn't find
any benefit on coronary artery
calcification between the vitamin K and
Placebo groups but they were using kind
of a small dose so these trials use a
whopping dose daily for a year and NADA
vitamin K supplementation did not
improve vascular stiffness or other
measures of artery health and in fact to
one study and the effect of vitamin K
supplementation on artery calcification
in patients with diabetes found that
calcification tended to increase after
supplementation to the type of vitamin K
found in a slimy fermented soy food
called natto now those with higher
levels of vitamin K circulating their
bloodstreams do tend to have lower
levels of inflammation but no wonder
where is Vitamin K found the predominant
dietary form of vitamin K in the human
diet comes from dark green leafy
vegetables and cruciferous vegetables so
how did people get high levels in their
blood eating broccoli those with higher
levels of vitamin K in their blood
reading more vegetables Less meat no
wonder they had lower levels of
inflammation
the recommended adequate daily intake
for Vitamin K is set at 70 micrograms a
day in Europe between 90 and 120 a day
here in the United States just two
leaves of kale has over 70 and a quarter
cup of cooked kale will get anyone all
the K they need for the day
now there is Vitamin K found in meat
Dairy and eggs averaging about 5 to 10
micrograms per serving in other words
they are even beaten out by Iceberg
Lettuce which is mostly water but still
contains like two to three times more
vitamin K
ah but that's vitamin K1 what's found in
animal products is mostly vitamin K2
do you need K2 apparently not once you
get enough plant-based K1 there's no
established requirement for K2 because
it hasn't been proven that K2 has
effects that are different from K1 they
both act the same way in the body thus
there's not even enough data to take K2
into account at all so in the
recommended adequate daily intakes are
set they're only talking about getting
enough K1 from Plants mostly green
vegetables
in fact most of the bone trials that
flopped used the K2 found in animal
products and most of the failed heart
studies used K2 as well okay even though
there's presently a lack of randomized
trial evidence to support a beneficial
role for vitamin K and preventing the
worsening of cardiovascular disease or
bone health what if that were to change
what if all of a sudden K2 was shown to
have unique benefits well guess what the
bacteria in your gut make k2 that's why
fermented foods have K2 bacteria make it
and the bacteria in your gut modeling
make it but it gets absorbed from your
colon up into your system contributing a
significant amount of the human vitamin
K requirement just in case you miss a
couple days of greens
vitamin K1 is made by plants and is the
primary dietary form Then There are a
dozen or so types of vitamin K2 which
are synthesized by bacteria including
several types in the human gut the
exception though is a type of K2 called
monoquinone 4 MK4 which is endogenously
synthesized in mammals and therefore is
found in animal products now I don't
know if any of you noticed but were
mammals too it has consistently been
shown that vitamin K1 from greens is
endogenously converted inside your body
to the vitamin K2 in animal products
you're made out of meat too though it
took until 2010 before we discovered the
human biosynthetic enzyme that does it
so no reason at all to take any sort of
vitamin K supplement Eat Your Greens in
fact when K2 supplements were looked at
researchers found significant problems
in terms of contaminants and mislabeling
Eat Your Greens
now K2 appears in higher concentrations
in certain tissues including the brain
again we make k2 from the K1 we eat in
Greens but maybe extra K2 might help
well if you measure vitamin K levels in
the blood and brains of centenarians
those that live over a hundred
concentrations of circulating K1 from
vegetables but not cerebral K2 not the
K2 in the brain was positively
correlated with a wide range of
cognitive measures why likely because
they're eating green vegetables and
green vegetables don't just have vitamin
K green leafy vegetables are the most
concentrated source of lutein the Eye
Health nutrient that's taken up into the
brain and is associated with cognitive
performance across the lifespan and so
in the centenarians circulating K1 and
lutein concentrations were highly
correlated so it's hard to tease out
exactly what in Greens was so beneficial
it's like when you see data showing
lower circulating K1 levels in the
bloodstream are associated with the
increased risk of all-cause mortality
meaning lower K1 levels were correlated
with a shorter lifespan well duh K1 is
found in Greens and of all the dietary
components correlated with all cause
mortality the best evidence appears to
support the intake of green leafy
vegetables and salads to reduce all
cause mortality in other words
Eat Your Greens
[Music]